Some of the most valuable wisdom in
investing exists in the form of short
quotes that distill hard-earned
experience and knowledge from expert
practitioners and academics into a
handful of words. In this video, I'm
going to tell you what I think are the
most important quotes in investing.
Quotes that every investor can and
should learn from, why they're
important, and how they can be applied
to everyday financial decisions. I'm Ben
Felix, chief investment officer at PWL
Capital, and I'm going to tell you what
we can learn from some of the most
important quotes in investing.
[Music]
For the first quote, we need to start
with something that is often
underappreciated in investing. Saving.
Saving is a necessary precondition for
investing. And for many people, saving
will be far more impactful and more
reliably impactful than searching for
higher investment returns. This is
captured by a classic quote from the
richest man in Babylon and popularized
further by Dave Chilton in the wealthy
barber. Pay yourself first. The point is
that in order to even have a shot at
building wealth through investing, you
need to save money, to pay yourself
before you have the chance to give into
the societal, biological, and
psychological pressures that lead many
people to overspend. Automating your
savings is an effective approach.
Setting up payroll deductions directly
into a retirement account is a great way
to do this if that option is available
to you. Otherwise, setting up automatic
contributions from your bank account to
an investment account can get you to a
similar place. Figuring out how much to
save is a more complex issue. The
wealthy barber suggests saving 10% of
your income, but economists would
generally suggest saving less early on
in your career when less money is
available and more later as your income
increases. Some research has even gone
as far as suggesting that young people
should not be saving at all. I don't
have a strong opinion as long as you
have a plan in place to meet your
long-term goals. With savings out of the
way, we can start to think about
investing. Investing is as much a
psychological endeavor as it is a
financial one. It involves risk and
uncertainty about the future, which are
to an extent quantifiable financial
issues. But doing it well requires
overcoming the countless behavioral
biases that plague investors. Ben
Graham, one of the fathers of financial
analysis and of the investment
profession as a whole, wrote, "The
investor's chief problem and even his
worst enemy is likely to be himself."
There are some great quotes that address
the challenges posed by investor
psychology. John Templeton said, "The
four most expensive words in the English
language are," this time is different.
This quote is a powerful reminder that
regardless of the objective realities of
a situation, narratives can easily sway
people's investment decisions. During
periods of extreme positive returns,
investors search for explanations that
not only justify the often accompanying
high stock valuations, but also justify
their continued increases. Think of
periods like the dotcom bubble or more
recently the runup of prices in the
holdings of the ARKK ETF. Many of the
investors in those assets were buying
stocks at historically anomalous
valuations and were literally saying the
words Templeton cautioned against. This
time is different. The internet changes
everything. AI changes everything. The
same thing happens when markets decline.
Economist Jeremy Seagull wrote, "Fear
has a greater grasp on human action than
does the impressive weight of historical
evidence." I can tell you over and over
again, as I do on this channel, what the
historical data tell us about market
crashes and recoveries, but that won't
always be helpful when fear is in the
air. Investors create narratives about
why markets will not recover this time
because of whatever is causing prices to
decline. How many times did we hear
unprecedented during CO? It's important
to acknowledge that every time we see
extreme asset price increases or
decreases is different. The underlying
causes and accompanying narratives are
always unique, which is why they cause
asset prices to swing wildly. What
doesn't change is that expected returns
for risky assets are positive, and
valuations matter, at least eventually.
They're the closest thing to gravity in
financial markets. Investors who want to
capture expected returns over the long
term, need to mentally and financially
prepare for bad times and hold assets
they're not going to panic sell even
when things are not working out as
expected. Market declines are never just
abstract numbers on a screen. They're
psychologically challenging times
stemming from deeply emotional and
uncertain events. The CO 19 pandemic
wasn't just a market decline. It was
potentially the end of life as we knew
it. One way to stay grounded through
periods of extreme market conditions in
either direction is to have conviction
in your investment philosophy. David
Booth, co-founder of the academically
grounded fund company Dimensional Fund
Adviserss, said, "The most important
thing about an investment philosophy is
that you have one that you can stick
with." The insight here runs deep.
Financial markets have generally
rewarded long-term disciplined
investors. But many, if not most,
investors sabotage their own returns by
moving in and out of investment
strategies or styles at precisely the
wrong times. Even an objectively
suboptimal investment philosophy like
dividend focused investing might be the
optimal investment philosophy for some
people if the dividends help them to
stay disciplined. The difficult thing
about sticking with an investment
philosophy is that any strategy, no
matter how wellounded its underlying
philosophy is, can appear to be wrong
for long periods of time. I think ARK is
again a good example. When it was on its
big run, I heard from many previously
disciplined index investors who were
considering abandoning their entire
investment philosophy because the ARKK
narrative was so strong and its manager
took direct aim at index funds. Kathy
Wood said that flows into index funds
were the most massive misallocation of
capital in history and that index funds
are overweing the old companies at risk
of being disrupted while underweing the
disruptors which ArkK focuses on. For a
while, it seemed like she was right as
ARK skyrocketed, leaving market cap
weighted index funds in the dust. But it
eventually came back to earth, as tends
to happen. Anyone who bailed on their
index funds to chase ARK's returns after
it had posted its big gains got burned.
And this was the experience of a large
portion of the investors in that fund.
Here's the interesting thing, though.
investors in ARK who truly believed in
that investment philosophy, stuck with
it from before Kathy Wood was all over
the financial media due to ArkK's
incredible short-term performance and
didn't sell when it eventually crashed,
have actually done fine. I'm not
condoning that investment strategy. I
don't think it makes any sense at all
and I think it fundamentally
misunderstands the relationship between
technological innovation and stock
returns. But my point is that conviction
in any investment philosophy will be
tested over time. But as long as it
leads to a reasonably well- diversified
and lowcost portfolio, having an
investment philosophy that you can stick
with through good times and bad is
likely far more important than having
the perfect investment philosophy, which
unfortunately doesn't really exist. Even
investors with a solid investment
philosophy often get nervous about
market corrections. They may consider
going to cash to avoid them or delaying
investing new cash. Fund manager Peter
Lynch said, "Far more money has been
lost by investors preparing for
corrections or trying to anticipate
corrections than has been lost in
corrections themselves." This quote
reminds us that while market downturns
can hurt, at least in the short run, the
opportunity cost of not investing is
typically far more expensive. Investing
is inherently risky. It is this very
fact that results in positive expected
returns and at least historically
positive realized long-term returns. The
problem is that investors are myopic.
They worry about short-term fluctuations
even if they are not short-term
investors and they are loss averse.
After settling on an investment
philosophy and preparing for difficult
market conditions, one of the most
fundamental decisions that investors
need to make is how to allocate their
portfolios. How much in stocks versus
bonds? How much in the stock market of
each country? Which stocks within each
country? Eugene FMA offers a good
starting point. He said you have to talk
yourself out of the market portfolio. In
theory, the market portfolio, the market
capitalization weighted portfolio of all
assets is optimal for the average
investor. State Street estimates that
the investable global market portfolio
is about 45% public stocks, 21%
government bonds, 9% investment grade
corporate bonds, and a whole bunch of
other stuff including gold, real estate,
and private equity making up the
remaining 25%. I'm not suggesting people
should actually try to replicate the
market portfolio. But FMA's point is
that while there can be good reasons to
be different from the market, it's
important to be clear on what those
reasons are and why they apply to you
specifically. For example, a younger
person may hold more stocks because they
can bear more risk. Someone in a given
country might overweight their home
country stocks because they're more cost
and tax efficient to own, and someone
might avoid private equity altogether
due to the asset class's high fees and
lack of transparency. These kinds of
deviations from the market portfolio can
make a lot of sense, but it's still
useful to use the market portfolio as a
starting point. Talking yourself from
the market portfolio into owning only
three stocks should be really hard to
do, as should talking yourself into
large allocations to asset classes that
make up a small portion of the market
portfolio, like private equity. As
allocation is incredibly important
because it calibrates the amount of risk
you are taking. One of the reasons that
investors struggle with risk is that
they don't really understand what it is.
Risk is often discussed as volatility or
the magnitude of short-term declines in
asset values, but those are probably not
the best measures for long-term
investors. Charles Ellis, author of
Winning the Losers Game, said, "Risk is
not having the money you need when you
need it." This simple definition
captures the fact that risk can either
manifest as the inability to fund
short-term liquidity needs, highlighting
the importance of planning for near-term
expenses, for example, by not investing
money you need tomorrow in stocks. Or
risk can manifest as the inability to
fund future consumption, capturing the
importance of earning sufficient
expected returns to fund your
inflationadjusted spending in the
distant future. The funny thing is that
aversion to short-term volatility
exposes investors to more extreme
long-term risk. It is by taking on the
risk of volatile assets that investors
expect to earn higher long-term returns.
As Morgan Huzle, author of the
psychology of money, wrote, "Vatility is
the price of admission for higher
expected returns." Not being willing or
able to take on the volatility of higher
expected return assets like stocks can
impair your ability to meet your
long-term goals. Framing risk as the
probability of running out of money puts
emphasis on what long-term investors
should really be focused on. But even
having the right focus doesn't mean
you're going to get the outcome you
hoped for. No matter how good we think
our models are, the future is unknown
and unknowable. And that unknown future
is what we need to plan for. Theory and
long-term evidence can help point us in
the right direction, but they still
can't predict the future. This doesn't
just apply to investments, either. Life
has a way of throwing curveballs at you,
making it hard to plan for everything.
Economist Elroy Dimpson said, "Risk
means more things can happen than will
happen. Every financial plan should
account for the fact that we simply
cannot know the range of future outcomes
based on what has happened in the past
or what we expect to happen in the
future. Investors should maintain a
healthy respect for the fact that things
will not always work out the way that we
want them to, no matter how much data we
base our decisions on. The nature of
risk and uncertainty make investing and
planning for the long term inherently
uncomfortable. Financial product
manufacturers and active fund managers
know that volatility is a struggle for
investors and they are eager to sell you
solutions. Economist John Cochran wrote,
"When having dinner with lions, make
sure you're at the table, not on the
menu. If someone wants to sell you
something, a stock or a financial
product, you need to ask yourself why
they want to sell it to you. What do
they know that you don't? What's in it
for them and what's in it for you? Are
you entering into a mutually beneficial
transaction or are you about to be eaten
alive by the financial alliance? There
are a ton of financial products out
there that cater to the fears and biases
of retail investors in exchange for
ridiculously high fees and costs,
putting retail investors on the menu.
Structured products tend to be one of
the most egregious examples, using
complexity to shroud extremely high
embedded costs. This is important
because fees and costs are one of the
few things that investors can actually
control. John Bogle, the founder of
Vanguard, said, "The grim irony of
investing is that we investors as a
group not only don't get what we pay
for, we get precisely what we don't pay
for." Bogle is speaking to the fact that
in aggregate, investors have not
benefited from paying higher fees to
active fund managers who aim to beat the
market. Instead, they have
underperformed market indexes roughly by
the amount that they paid in fees. This
is what Bill Sharp has referred to as
the arithmetic of active management. As
a group, active funds must underperform
passive funds because both groups hold
the market, but active funds have
inherently higher fees and costs. This
grim reality cannot be escaped, but it's
not always obvious. Investing is a
discipline that due to its inherent risk
and uncertainty contains a lot of noise.
It is very difficult to be certain of
anything in financial markets other than
the fact that there will be a lot of
uncertainty. The next quote is generally
attributed to Mark Twain. It ain't what
you don't know that gets you into
trouble. It's what you know for sure
that just ain't so. One of the most
dangerous attributes in an investor is
overconfidence.
Anytime you think you are sure of
something, real estate always goes up.
This crypto token is going to the moon.
Tech stocks will always beat the market.
The US market will always outperform.
This fund manager is brilliant. And so
on. You've got to step back and remind
yourself that the only certainty in
investing is uncertainty. It's always
worth asking yourself what happens if
you're wrong. In addition to discipline
and psychological fortitude, successful
investing requires a good dose of
humility and skepticism. One of the best
ways to express humility in investing is
through diversification. If you go allin
on a single stock and end up being
wrong, you could be setting yourself
back permanently. It's not uncommon for
single stocks to drop 60% or more and
never recover. If you hold a broadly
diversified portfolio of stocks, the
risk of permanent capital impairment or
total loss is significantly reduced.
Harry Marowitz is paraphrased as saying,
"Diversification is the only free lunch
in investing." Typically, as I mentioned
earlier, volatility is the price of
admission for higher expected returns.
But diversification is a rare case where
adding multiple imperfectly correlated
risky assets together in a portfolio can
allow you to increase expected returns
without increasing risk or decrease risk
without decreasing expected returns.
Diversification also mitigates the
damage if a single investment in a
portfolio does not work out and it makes
you more likely to hold the rare big
winners that drive most of the market's
returns. The downside of diversification
is that it makes it less likely that
you'll hit big home runs. But due to the
skewess in individual stock returns,
that is the fact that most stocks
perform poorly while a relative few
perform exceptionally well, you're far
more likely to pick losing stocks than
to pick big winners. As John Bogle said,
"Don't look for the needle, by the
haststack." These quotes boil down to a
few key principles. Spend less than you
earn. Keep enough cash on hand for
near-term expenses and invest the
remainder in a risk appropriate
portfolio with expected returns
sufficient to meet your long-term goals.
Choose an investment philosophy and
asset allocation that you can stick with
even when they don't seem to be working.
Don't try to time the market. Be
prepared for the future to be different
from your current expectations. Be aware
of your fees and costs. Don't be too
sure of anything and diversify broadly.
Before I let you go, if you enjoyed this
video, I think you'll really like the
Rational Reminder podcast. We've
interviewed the originators of many of
the quotes mentioned in this video,
including Dave Chilton, David Booth,
Eugene FMA, Charles Ellis, Morgan Hel,
and John Cochran. It is consistently
ranked one of the top business and
investing podcasts in Canada, and I'd
love it if you checked it out. Thanks
for watching. I'm Ben Felix, chief
investment officer at PWL Capital. I'm
sure I missed some good ones, so please
post your favorite investing quotes in
the comments.